<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the iuglings and deceitfull impostures of a scandalous libell against the Parliament. Published in the forme of a petition to the Houses of Parliament, in the name of the inhabitants of London and Westminster, and inhabitants of Southwarke, pretended to be distressed in point of conscience. Hereunto is added the said petition, in the name of the inhabitants of London and Westminster, &amp;c. Together with a free, cleare and conscientious answer in way of petition, to the foresaid scandalous pamphlet.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E247_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81540)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 42:E247[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the iuglings and deceitfull impostures of a scandalous libell against the Parliament. Published in the forme of a petition to the Houses of Parliament, in the name of the inhabitants of London and Westminster, and inhabitants of Southwarke, pretended to be distressed in point of conscience. Hereunto is added the said petition, in the name of the inhabitants of London and Westminster, &amp;c. Together with a free, cleare and conscientious answer in way of petition, to the foresaid scandalous pamphlet.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>To the honourable Houses of Parliament The humble petition of the inhabitants of the cityes of London and Westminster, and the borough of Southwarke.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118171:1"/>
            <head>THE Petition in the Name of the Inhabitants of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminſter,</hi> And the Borough of <hi>Southwarke,</hi> In the behalfe of themſelves, and of Millions in this Kingdome, diſtreſſed in point of Conſcience.</head>
            <p>WHereas your Petitioners having formerly contributed, freely and literally to the King and Parliament in coniunction, deo now refuſe further to contribute or pay, conceiving them in oppoſition; as by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon His Maieſties perſon was invaded in battell at <hi>Keinton</hi> (contrary to the many Declarations of taking of Armes for the ſafety of His Maieſtieſties perſon) ſo in regard theat is no expreſſe care of His perſon and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in your late Ordinance, for the aſſeſſing the Twentieth part in <hi>London,</hi> nor in your Declaration for levying of moneyes in the Counties.</p>
            <p>And whereas this their refuſall is meerely out of Conſcience, according to that information they have concerning the Divine conſtitution of particular Kings in their ſeverall Kingdomes, and of Subiection to them both Active and Paſſive, and of the Damnableneſſe of Reſiſting; from</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Word of God: <hi>Dan. 4.17. &amp; 25.32.</hi> where thrice in one Chapter it is ſaid, That the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes be Gods, and he gives them to whom he will. <hi>1 Sam 26.9.</hi> Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Annointed and be guiltleſſe. And the ſame bleſſed ſpirit which calls <hi>David</hi> the Lords Annoynted, <hi>Pſalm 89.20.</hi> doth call <hi>Cyrus</hi> a Heathen Prince the Lords Annoynted alſo. <hi>Eſa 45.1. Rom. 13.</hi> Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God; The Powers that be are ordained of God, whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation (Yea we acknowledge in our Book of Common Prayer that King <hi>Charles</hi> is Gods Miniſter, and that he hath Gods Authority, and ſo fighting againſt him, we fight againſt God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, M. <hi>Calvin</hi> and other Proteſtants, their expoſition on <hi>Rom. 13. &amp; 1 Pet 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Harmony of Reformed Churches concerning Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Bookes of Homilies delivered, concerning civill obedience.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, From the Lawes of the Land, which declare it to be Treaſon to Levy Warre againſt the King in this Kingdome, and to encounter in fight, and kill ſuch as are aſſiſting to the King, or come to helpe him, or to aide in thoſe caſes.</p>
            <p>And the Action of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> was adiudged Treaſon, though he pretended nothing but removing evill Councellours from the Queene. Now that which is evill in its owne nature cannot be the ſubiect of any Command, nor induce any obligation upon any man by any Authority whatſoever. Remonſtrance <hi>May 19.</hi> And we may not doe evill that good may come of it, <hi>Rom. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, Alſo in regard of the late Proteſtation, relating to the ſaid Doctrines, and to His Maieſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, which Proteſtation, you have bound your ſelves to maintaine, and all thoſe that doe any thing in purſuance of it.</p>
            <p>You would at leaſt be pleaſed in your preſent undertakings for Religion, and for the Law of the Land, and the Liberty and Property of the Subiects, to proceed in the way of Religion without violence to the Conſcience, in a caſe that concernes no leſſe then Salvation or Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (As you profeſſe your tenderneſſe of the Conſcience even in matters of Indifferency) And that firſt your Authenticall Divines (D. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> M. <hi>Marſhall, &amp;c.</hi>) may publiſh ſomething for the reſolving of Conſcience in this way cleerely out of the Word of God, and home to the Action of <hi>Keinton,</hi> taking notice alſo, That his Maieſty tooke up Armes for the maintenance of the Lawes, concerning the publick worſhip of God, and for the priviledges of and freedome of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, notoriouſly invaded by Browniſts and Separatiſts; and that now He continues them alſo for the neceſſary defence of His Perſon, manifeſtly in danger ſince the battle at <hi>Keinton.</hi> To which (ſatiſfying the Premiſes) your Petitioners (farre from contemptuouſneſſe and obſtinacy againſt the cleere Word of God and Lawfull Authority) ſhall ingeniouſly condeſcend; and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily make payment of theſe ſeverall Rates accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>And pray for,</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:118171:1"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of the juglings and deceitfull impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of a ſcandalous Libell againſt the <hi>Parliament:</hi> Publiſhed in the forme of a Petition to the Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> In the Names, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of the Libellous paper, ſtiled, <hi>A Petition to the Houſes of Parliament</hi> of the Inhabitants of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and <hi>Bourough</hi> of <hi>Southwarke,</hi> in the behalfe of themſelvs and of millions in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſtreſſed in point of conſcience, like the Devill diſguiſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in <hi>Samuels</hi> mantle, and takes upon him the forme of an Angell of light, pretending conſcience, and falſely perſonating the honeſt inhabitants of thoſe Cities and that Bourough, who remaine to all poſterity and future ages, juſtly and worthily renowned for their love and zeale to Religion, the liberties of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the great and chiefe conſervator of them under Heaven. But you may diſcerne him by the cloven foote by which he enters into his Petition, deviding it ſelfe into two apparent lyes, one that he hath freely and liberally contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> conjoyn'd, and the other, that his Majeſties Perſon was invaded in battle at <hi>Keinton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The grounds of his pretended conſcience are of like nature manifeſtly fallacious; for firſt, in his Scriptures cited by him, as the Devill did in tempting our Saviour, he changes divine truth into a lye by curtailing it: For it is true, God gives Kingdomes to whom he will, but it is not all the truth, for God alſo gives them in ſeverall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with ſeverall ſorts of power, Some Kingdomes he gives to one man alone, and inveſts him with abſolute power that his will is law, which is commonly called an Abſolute Monarchy: But ſuch power he hath not given to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (as this man would have us beleeve) His Majeſty in his Declarations diſclaimes it, and pretends to no other power then to governe according to the Lawes made by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power of this Kingdome, reſiding by divine providence and ordinance in the three eſtates, which are coordinate, and not ſubordinate in authority, though the truſt of convening them, be by them committed to the <hi>King,</hi> in confidence that he will according to Law, call them together when there ſhall be neede thereof for the Kingdomes good; and in the meane time, ſee to a juſt execution of the Lawes made by them: And when Parliaments are conveened, to them belongs the care of the Kingdome, and of the Lawes, and the examining, puniſhing and reforming of whatſoever is done againſt the Lawes and Kingdome by the <hi>Kings</hi> perſonall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or pretence of his authority. And farewell Religion, Law, Liberty, and all good, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> be and continue obſtructed as now it is, from queſtioning, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining, or puniſhing and reforming things done againſt Law, by colour and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the <hi>Kings</hi> Perſonall will (which is ſubject to be deceived, miſled, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to the prejudice of the ſubject. And they have alſo power to provide and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the <hi>Kings</hi> royall aſſent further Lawes profitable for the Kingdome. And he that reſiſts theſe powers of <hi>Parliament,</hi> though it be the <hi>King</hi> himſelfe, or by colour of his command, <hi>reſiſts the powers ordained of God, and the ordinance of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.15. lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and the revin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication thereof.</note> falſifies the late <hi>Proteſtation, and ſhall receive for it</hi> (if the word of God be true) <hi>damnation without repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the annoynting of <hi>Kings,</hi> before Chriſt exhibited, it was commanded and uſed, as the annoynting of Prieſts and Prophets, becauſe tipicall of the true annoynted Jeſus Chriſt, in his Kingly, Prieſtly, and Propheticall offices. But now thereis neither rule, uſe or neceſſity of any ſuch annoynting, Chriſt and his members being the only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted of the Lord under the Goſpell. <hi>Romans</hi> 13. commands <hi>every ſoule</hi> (even
<pb facs="tcp:118171:2"/>
               <hi>Kings</hi> where they be not the ſupreame power) <hi>to be ſubject to the higher powers:</hi> ſo as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is, and ought to be ſubject to the Lawes, which are the powers eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the 3 eſtates, for the regulating of all perſons and things within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not alterable by the <hi>Kings</hi> power which is ſubordinate and given him by the Lawes, and by them ſupported and conſerved unto him. And this Scripture ſpeakes only of powers: Legall commands have power in them, and are to be ſubjected unto, but illegall commands are the ſins and weakeneſſes of the perſonall will of the <hi>King,</hi> and are not to be ſubmitted unto, and the authour of this Libell hath by chance ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled upon a reaſon for it, where he ſaith, that that which is evill cannot be the ſubject of any command, nor induce any obligation upon any man by any authority.</p>
            <p>It is certaine that King <hi>Charles</hi> is Gods Miniſter while he executes the Lawes which are the immediate iſſues of the ſupreame power the 3 eſtates, and ſo he hath Gods authority, but <hi>where he proceeds by a deceived and miſled will againſt the Laws, he is</hi> ſaith the Lawyer, <hi>the minister of the Devill</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton:</hi> Miniſter Diaboli.</note>. And to fight againſt ſuch as take up Armes againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to protect themſelves and other offenders againſt the Lawes, and to hinder and obſtruct the ſaid lawfull powers and priviledges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> is to fight for God and the powers ordained by him: and ſuch as take up Armes againſt ſuch powers of <hi>Parliament,</hi> though they have the perſonall commands of the <hi>King</hi> for it, doe fight againſt Gods authority, and againſt God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from <hi>Calvin</hi> and the harmony of reformed Churches concerning Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, nothing can be produced in any wiſe, contrary to what I have ſaid; and if this Authour had expreſſed what they ſay, it would have evidently appeared, and both their writings and practiſes cleerely confirme it, and the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> cannot be conceived to fight againſt the Laws and politick Monarchy of <hi>England.</hi> But this deceivers wicked purpoſe to delude his readers, is further expreſſed by his hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe in generalls, and ſhunning the cleere directing and convincing light of diſtinct knowledge.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The law declaratory of Treaſon is the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Which firſt declares it to be Treaſon, to compaſſe or imagine the <hi>Kings</hi> death. Secondly, To levy war againſt the <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt provides for the <hi>Kings</hi> ſafety in his Perſon: and the other for his <hi>Kingly</hi> power, that it be not obſtructed by the hand of force and violence. And as to reſcue the <hi>Kings</hi> Perſon out of the hands of enemies or thieves by force of Armes, and to fight againſt them that wickedly captivate and carry him away, is not any offence againſt the firſt branch of this Statute: So to raiſe Armes and to fight againſt them that reſiſt and obſtruct his moſt eminent power which is in his <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and Laws, is not any offence againſt the latter. And they that by wicked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſeduce the <hi>King</hi> from the <hi>Parliament</hi> and from his Lawes, and his care of ſeeing them executed, to the danger and dammage of his Kingdome, and from his Oath by which he is obliged to both, and draw him to adventure his Perſon in moſt imminent dangers, to protect them in their rebellion againſt the Law and juſt puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the high Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> are cleerely Traitors within the firſt branch of this Statute. And they that take up Armes to obſtruct and oppoſe the Lawes and juſtice of the Kingdome, and the due execution thereof, are evidently Traitors within the other branch thereof, which is meant of the <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>politick capacity</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rex eſt Nomen officij.</note>, his legall Kingly authority, moſt eminently exerciſed, and apparent in his high Court of <hi>Parliament:</hi> This latter clauſe being diſtinct in ſence and meaning from that former concerning his Perſon. And I confidently beleeve, every man not wilfully blinded by malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and goodneſſe, will eaſily grant that the King may be more certaine and aſſured of ſafety in <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and of Angellicall protection in the way of his Kingly office and duty, then in the hands and power of the Dammees, that for their wicked and damned baſe ends, pretend to aſſiſt and helpe him in wayes contrary to his office, and deſtructive to his Kingdome and people.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118171:2"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in taking up Armes againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to remove ſuch from her as he counted his Enemies, offended againſt the ſaid Statute, becauſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a private quarrell againſt ſome Peeres and great Officers neere about the Queenes Perſon, he being a private man without legall authority, and contrary to Law took up Armes and raiſed force to goe to the Queenes Court, to the apparent endangering of her royall Perſon, and ſo it was in Law, both an imagining of her death, and a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of War againſt the Law and her regall power. But how impertinently, yea malitiouſly this is applyed to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> preſent caſe, is manifeſt to him that hath but halfe an eye. The difference betweene the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> is no private quarrell, the <hi>Parliament</hi> which is no private perſon, but the higheſt Court of juſtice in the Kingdom, the repreſentative body of the Kingdome, to whom the preſervation of the Kingdome, and of the peace and ſafety thereof and of the Lawes, doth properly and primarily belong, diſcovering ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> wicked men practiſing to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Parliament</hi> and our Laws and liberties, by falſe and ſcandalous aſperſions caſt upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and lying ſuggeſtions againſt the power of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the proceedings and priviledges thereof, whiſpered into the eares of the <hi>King,</hi> to ſeduce and draw him away from his <hi>Parliament,</hi> and his affections from his people, to improve his Perſonall illegall commands, to reſiſt and fruſtrate the lawfull procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of his <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt them, to withdraw the great Seale from them, and the members of either Houſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> from their attendance upon the ſervice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to raiſe a force againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> not only to ſhelter themſelves from the hand of juſtice, and keepe the good ſubjects from all uſe and benefit of the Laws, and deſtroy their properties by forcible pillaging and plundring (which every man ſees to be the ends of their ſaid practiſes, and therefore firſt in their intentions) but alſo <hi>Alexander</hi> like, by the Sword to cut the gordian knot they could not otherwiſe untie, I meane to deſtroy this perpetuall <hi>Parliament,</hi> before the grievances of the Kingdome contracted before by their wicked counſels be redreſſed, that the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion intended and deſired, ſhall never receive birth and perfection, diſtilling into the <hi>Kings</hi> mind a wicked and irrationall conceit, that a perpetuall <hi>Parliament</hi> and his Kingly office and power cannot conſiſt. The <hi>Parliament</hi> I ſay to defend themſelves and the Kingdome from theſe diabolicall deſignes and practiſes, and to bring theſe grand-Delinquents to juſtice, and reſcue his Majeſty out of their hands, tooke up Armes, and at <hi>Keinton</hi> and elſe where made uſe thereof. Shall the <hi>Parliaments</hi> performance of their duty and truſt become Treaſon or unlawfull? by what Lawes, reaſon or ſence? Is it no Treaſon for an inferiour Court to raiſe force, to execute the Proces thereof, though the <hi>King</hi> expreſſe his Perſonall will ever ſo ſtrongly even under his great Seale to the contrary? and ſhall it be unlawfull or treaſonable in the ſupreame Court to do it, which hath power to ſtay and check the proceedings of all inferiour Courts, which the <hi>King</hi> cannot doe by his Perſonall command.</p>
            <p>Hereby may appeare that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath proceeded in the way of Religion in this great caſe, and this Libeller hath his deſire, but that he cannot ſee the wood for trees; and there is no need of troubling ſuch able Divines as he Names to convince his ignorance, they are or may be better imployed. And for Browniſts and Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, it is notorious that the <hi>Kings</hi> taking up Armes is ſo farre from being againſt them, as it is the only cauſe that wholeſome proviſions for the right governing of the Church are not made and ſetled, that they may be ſuppreſſed and wholy rooted out, and that they are fomented, incouraged and increaſed daily, by the continuance of thoſe Forces in obſtruction of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> power and proceedings againſt them. If a right diſcipline according to Gods word, and a painefull preaching Miniſtery were once ſetled in this Kingdome, ſuch Sectaries and Schiſmaticks would be quickly ſubdued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118171:3"/>
            <head>To the two moſt honourable Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative body of the moſt glorious legitime, and Chriſtian Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> the humble Petition of ſome Well affected Patriots diſperſed here and there.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there is a Petition ſpread abroad, pretending the number of millions, alledging diſtreſſe of conſcience, who in all likelihood ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver felt any, except in the feare of a pure Reformation, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by their verball arguments, abuſing the Scripture to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick end, <hi>(viz.) Dan.</hi> 4.17.25.32. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 89.20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.1. with the Booke of Common Prayers, attributing to the King Gods authority; from which they urge a literall appearance to their own over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and the enſlaving of all to more then Turkiſh ſervitude: Not underſtanding, or conſidering that <hi>Cirus</hi> is onely ſtiled God Annoynted in a figurative phraſe, for the ſervice of Chriſt whereunto he was deſtined, even the reſtauration of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; otherwiſe no more the Lords Annoynted, then was <hi>Eglon</hi> King of <hi>Moab,</hi> whom <hi>Ehud</hi> ſtab'd to the heart, for the deliverance of Gods Church and people, <hi>Jud.</hi> 3.12.19, 20, 21. Then groſſely diſtorting that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. for though it be onely a direction unto particular Chriſtians, that they ſhould not (living under ſuch govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ordinance) abuſe their Chriſtian liberty to the ſcandall of profeſſion or the Goſpell, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16. yet would theſe politick gloſſers, hereby over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the irrationall rabble, if not to a rebellious oppoſition againſt, at the leaſt, to an abſolute diſdaine and deſertion of Gods ordinance (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2.) a neceſſary counſell and indiſſoluble, by the people elected, and the King eſtabliſhed, as the onely ſoule and intelligence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> State, the laſt remedy and only ſecurity againſt thoſe pernicious ſeducers, and crafty politicians which alwayes aime more at their owne ends, then either at the publike good or their Maſters honour; authorized thereby (if our Divinity and reaſon faile us not, <hi>Prov: ch.</hi> 25.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.27.) not only to the declaring of Law, but the executing of that, which being according to the divine Law and our municipall right, (no way thwarting the principles of nature or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall reaſon) doth beſt conduce to the enfranchizing of the Goſpell and worſhip, from all ſervile bonds and ſuperſtitious obligations, the eſtabliſhing of the ſubject in his true and native liberty, the King and his Progeny in a conſtant glory and durable felicity. And whereas theſe deceitfull workers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 15. pretend the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine conſtitution of particular Kings in their ſeverall Kingdomes. This ſhaddow of reaſon they have greedily catched from the ſuperficiall Pamphlets of Court paraſites, who being infected with that Popiſh errour, (in the cacozelous imitation of the <hi>Aaronicall</hi> Prieſthood, which was firſt practiſed by that flattering Pope who annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Charles</hi> the Great unto the Empire,) and then madded to aſtoniſhment, with the eye dazeling ſplendour of Courtly glory, they would of a King create a demi-god, though to the utter ſubverſion of the Churches rights, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> glory, and the ſcope of Scriptures (as ſhall be maintained againſt them in a faire diſpute at the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of life upon defailance) Thus (we ſay) infatuate and made furious, they would foſter in the people a pernicious opinion of the Kings ſuperiority, not only to the State (as it is now eſtabliſhed) But to the Church alſo, which is Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, truly ſo called according to the tenour of the old and new Teſtament, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, with 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. and the apple of his eye, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8. for whoſe liberty, protection and edification, the King (as chiefe member of the ſame) is
<pb facs="tcp:118171:3"/>tyed by the tenour of his Baptiſme, for the maintaining of unity and uniformity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of charity, and a ſincere conſcience regulated by the word, to improve all the power and prerogative wherewith be is veſted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.7, 23. with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. Tho' theſe prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> renouncing both their Baptiſme and birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, would make gracious Princes, of nurſing Fathers, to become hard Maſters, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizing over the Church, by their Praelaticall vaſſals, who, ever contrary to their office and the Kings authority (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2, 3.) are found to have ſhorne the ſheepe of Chriſts paſture to the quick, under pretext of ſuppreſſing ſome ſilly fantaſticall Sectaries, who in their obſtinate ſelf particular humours are more ſhame then aſſiſtance to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and inſenſibly ſide with the Caviliers deſigne, being much more juſtly and effectually to be quell'd, by a ſincerely judicious Synod, and found government ſutable to the word, then either by an high Commiſſion or any ſervile and typhonicall Synod derived from the Kings Supremacy. By this meanes alſo doe they wickedly indeavour to reflect ſome guilt upon you, If in the purſuance of the moſt juſt and holy reſolutions (which) being qualified according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion aforeſaid, under correction we conceive that the King is bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (<hi>rebus &amp; Statutis ita ſtantibus,</hi> not only to aſſent and imbrace, but alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote with all his prerogative) his Majeſty ſhould receive any Perſonall dammage, tho' againſt your wills and ardent Petitions, and the expreſſe deſire of all thoſe, that are not for their own intereſt very ill affected, to his true honour and ſafety; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by all reaſon and Scripture it appeareth, that all the blame is to be laid upon thoſe, who ſeek to ſeduce him, ſo wilfully to adventure himſelfe, in ſuch ſociety as threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the wrath of God and deſtruction upon him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.7, 8. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. with 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.21, 22. And to bolſter up their traiterous babble, contriv'd to the ruine of Kingdom and State, they alledge the Doctrine of the Church, in the Booke of Homilies, as if the Authors or publiſhers of thoſe godly Treatiſes, could determine of a caſe, which rightly ſtated, never till this time, came within any <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans ſuppoſall; And ſo either very ſimply or very ſubtilly, doe they urge M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Calvins</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the Harmony of reformed Churches concerning Magiſtracy, All of which Divines, give as much authority (over the Church) to their Ariſtocratians, as they acknowledge can be due by any condition, to the moſt Catholike Crowne or triple Tiara; And for the preſent have and doe ſtand in ſuch an oppoſition to Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchy, that if their reſiſtance be but lawfull, ours now, muſt needs be abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit and neceſſary. Yet let us once ſee a free Synod, and in this particular we will ſtand to the Arbitration of thoſe Divines which ſhall be rightly choſen, and ſent from the reformed Churches. Then doe they preſume to give ſence to the Laws of the Land againſt that Soveraigne (as of late in ſome caſes we have ſeene) Authority of interpretation, which now reſideth in you (as we think) by the peoples election and (Kings confirmation of you, as the only competent Judges of the Laws, betweene himſelfe and his people, then not only diſſenting but diffiding.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They are not aſhamed to urge the Proteſtation, which ſome who refuſed to take it, doe abſolutely averre: That no man ever intending their courſe or way, could at any time receive or vow to performe, except guilty, either of acauterized conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or blockiſh ſtupidity. We therefore ſeriouſly pondering the deplorable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of Church and State, And that not one of a 1000 but from ſelf intereſt, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the King in this ruinous quarrell; the inſatiable deſires of which aſſiſtants our lives and fortunes can never ſatisfie, as the Malignants themſelves ſhall find, when up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſucceſſe, they feele them encreaſe as they are repleniſhed. 2. How the muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roome
<pb facs="tcp:118171:4"/>or mongrell Gentry begin to emulate their inferiours, and what they cannot effect by emulation, they endeavour by malice. 3. That their zealous ambition to rule the Puritans, mortally exaſperates many to the ſlaughter of thoſe, who when they are dead cannot be ruled. Fourthly, That calumnies goe high in reputation whilſt accuſations are at a loſſe, and liberty of language ſtands upon her triall, the moſt hatefull thing to a crue of tyrants, becauſe the moſt neceſſary to a Commonwealth, as that upon (which the libertie of life dependeth. 5. That the Church can never be ſetled by any Papall power derived from the Crowne Imperiall, (to which it is by Law annexed) without offering dangerous and damnable violence to 1000000<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. of conſciences. 6. That now we muſt be made truly free, or elſe tyed to an abſolute ſervitude. 7. That union in Religion and uniformity in Kirk government agreed upon in both the Kingdomes with his Majeſties approbation, can never be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed till you either reduce into <hi>Scotland</hi> the preſidentiall Prelacy, or admit a lawfull and canonicall Presbitery into <hi>England.</hi> 8. That his Majeſties Perſon is in danger, not from you (who ſeeke nothing but his glory and preſervation, tho' in a way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his humour and appetite.) But of thoſe Swords that now ſeeme to defend him, whoſe mercinary ſouls upon any pang of paſſion or private hope, may eaſily be provok't to a bloudy enterpriſe, from which we daily pray that God may alwaies deliver his gracious Majeſty. Thus pauſing upon the premiſes, and well weying that Kingly ordinance is of God, (who is never the authour of confuſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. but alwayes of peacefull order, be it popular, Ariſtocraticall or Monarchicall each of which ſtill remaining in its formality an humane ordinance 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. And of its own nature alſo alterable) and that by wiſedome only Kings reigne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. the Scripture ſecuring their honour and authority, only upon their piety towards God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.5. and adminiſtration of juſtice in all equity towards man, <hi>Jer</hi> 22.15. threatning them with certaine ruine, ready every way to runne in upon them whenſoever they ſhall abuſe their power to Idolatry, injuſtice or tyranny, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24 17, 24. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.4, 7. <hi>Job</hi> 12.18, 19, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.40. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Iſa</hi> 40.23. with <hi>Dan</hi> 4.23, 24. Tho' prophane politicians by adulations ſuperbiate Princes to the deniall of this, whilſt in a formality of words they ſeeme to confeſſe it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them in very deed to arrogate all unto themſelves, the acquiring and retaining of Kingdomes to their wicked arts and policies; by the which arrogance, Princes often bring ruine upon themſelves, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.7, 8, 12, 13, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.10, 11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8 9 Wicked ſycophants abuſing thoſe Scriptures to patronize tyranny, which the ſpirit intended as ſtrongeſt provocations unto piety, in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance whereof Principalitie may alwayes remaine, ſo ſecure and impregnable, that Souldiers ſhall only ſerve to adorne its State, not ſecure the Perſon: And doating po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.13. not diſcerning this, attribute often to the iniquity of people what redoundeth unto Princes by the juſt judgement of God, <hi>Chap</hi> 25 27. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a tender care of the Kings ſafety, and for the preſervation of our Religion and liberties, We humbly crave that you would be pleaſed to proceed on unto that exact Reformation which you promiſed, manger the underminings of ſpirtefull Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, whoſe fraudulent contexture and artificiall concinnity catcheth the common ſort, even to the ruine and infection of our Kingdome (as anciently hath appeared in the thrice renowned <hi>Graecia</hi>) if your wiſedome and conſtant reſolution prevent it not, by rendering to his Majeſty (as ſo many noble Ephories by him ſo graciouſly eſtabliſhed now in <hi>England</hi>) a more glorious and durable Kingdom, And ſuch as the moſt prudent <hi>Theopompus</hi> chooſe to leave to his own poſterity, notwithſtanding the bitter repining of female ambition lodging in his boſome,</p>
            <closer>And your humble Petitioners ſhall continue their prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
